Guide to the Stanley Person Baseball Collection BCMS.0065
Brooklyn Collection
Stanley Person Baseball Collection
1926-1994
Brooklyn Collection
BCMS.0065
6.2 Linear feet in 6 baseball boxes, 2 document boxes, 1 half size document box, 1 postcard box, 1 oversize flat box
This collection includes tickets, programs, photographs, postcards, autographed baseballs, and other memorabilia from various baseball teams. Items from the National Baseball Hall of Fame and postcards depicting various New York City buildings and bridges are also included.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series:
Series I: Brooklyn Dodgers is arranged in six subseries by type. Folders within each subseries are arranged alphabetically, baseballs are arranged chronologically.
Series II: Non-Brooklyn Baseball Items is arranged in six subseries by type. Folders within each subseries are arranged alphabetically.
Series III: Non-Baseball Photographs and Prints is contained in two folders with no item arrangement.
Access
Collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at the Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Provenance
This collection was donated by Diane Person in March 2004, with additional materials donated in June 2005.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of this collection comprises items from various baseball teams including the Brooklyn Dodgers, Los Angeles Dodgers, and New York Yankees. Items from the Brooklyn Dodgers include autographed baseballs from the 1941-1957 seasons, tickets, game programs, and trading cards. Photographs and postcards depict players, staff and Ebbets Field. Additional baseball items include various team programs, tickets, postcards, and stamps, as well as general baseball trivia books.
Items from the National Baseball Hall of Fame and postcards depicting various New York City buildings and bridges are also included.
Historical Note
The origins of baseball may trace to the games of cricket and rounders, played in Great Britain as early as the 15th century. British colonists began playing similar ball and bat games, with the first mentions of "baste ball" and "baseball" appearing in the United States the late 18th century. Abner Doubleday is often credited with inventing modern baseball in Cooperstown, New York, however it's now believed his involvement was exaggerated, perhaps in an attempt to establish baseball as a solely American sport. Modern baseball rules were written in 1845 by Alexander Cartwright, who also founded The Knickerbockers, a New York City baseball club that played in the first officially recorded baseball game on June 19, 1846 at the Elysian Fields in Hoboken, New Jersey.
Over the next 30 years amateur teams were formed all over the country, leading to the creation of The National Association of Base Ball Players, which counted over 400 clubs by 1867. In 1869 the Cincinnati Red Stockings were established as the sport's first professional team, causing a rift between the professional and amateur players. The National Association of Professional Baseball Players formed in 1871 as baseball's first attempt at an all professional league. Frustrations over rule breaking and contract jumping lead to the formation of splinter leagues, including the National Base Ball League in 1876 and the Western League, which became the American League in 1901. The National League and the American League currently make up Major League Baseball (MLB), the oldest professional sports league in the United States.
Baseball clubs were introduced to Kings County as early as the 1820s, with over 71 amateur teams playing in the county by 1851. Early prominent clubs included the Atlantics and the Ekfords, drawing players from the blue collar workforce and attracting thousands of fans to games played all over the borough. In 1883, Charles Byrne opened the Washington Park baseball field on 5th Avenue and 3rd Street in Park Slope and formed a team called the Brooklyn Grays. The team joined the American Association in 1884 and the National League in 1890, by which time they were known as the Bridegrooms.
In 1891 Washington Park burned down and the team was moved to Eastern Park, a 12,000 seat stadium in Brooklyn's Brownsville neighborhood. The team was still known as the Bridegrooms but picked up several nicknames including the Superbas and the Brooklyn Trolley Dodgers, named after borough residents who had to "dodge" oncoming electric trollies. In 1898 Byrne died and was succeeded by his assistant, Charlie Ebbets. By 1899 Ebbets gained majority control over the team and in 1912 moved them to Ebbets Field, a new 37,000 seat stadium in Flatbush.
The team played and lost their first World Series game in 1916, in front of the largest crowd in baseball history. By 1920 the team was officially known as the Brooklyn Dodgers, but was also called the Daffiness Boys, a nickname reflective of their performance on the field and outrageous behavior of players and management. The death of Charlie Ebbets in 1925 left the team open to poor management and a series of disastrous trades that led to a drop in ticket sales and a field in need of repairs. Things began to turn around in 1938 when Leland MacPhail was brought in as General Manager. MacPhail got rid of the Daffiness Boys and replaced them with some of the Dodgers' most iconic players, including Pee Wee Reese and Pete Reiser.
When the U.S. entered World War II MacPhail and several players enlisted. Branch Rickey was brought in from St. Louis as the new General Manager. In 1947 he signed Jackie Robinson, the first black man to play on a major league baseball team. The 1947 season kicked off an era often called the "glory days" with star players including Roy Campanella, Duke Snider and Gil Hodges. Brooklyn supported their team with steady game attendance, merchandise sales and their own fight song, "Follow the Dodgers." After years of close-calls and near-misses the team finally captured a World Series title in the 1955 season.
After 43 years Ebbets Field was in a state of disrepair and team owner Walter O'Malley began to make plans for a new stadium in Brooklyn. O'Malley's plan for a city subsidized stadium at the intersection of Flatbush and Atlantic Avenue that would provide more seats, parking and access to public transportation was rejected by Robert Moses, who proposed an alternative location in Queens, the eventual site of Shea Stadium. O'Malley began negotiations with the city of Los Angeles, which promised a growing market and space for a new stadium. The National League authorized the move on May 28, 1957 and the Los Angeles Dodgers played their first game on April 18, 1958.
Related Archival Materials note
Al Todres Brooklyn Dodgers Collection
Photographs from our Digital Collections
Golenbock, Peter. Bums--an oral history of the Brooklyn Dodgers. Putnam, 1984.
Krell, David. "Our bums": the Brooklyn Dodgers in history, memory and popular culture. McFarland & Company, Inc., Publishers, 2015.
McGee, Bob. The greatest ballpark ever: Ebbets Field and the story of the Brooklyn Dodgers. Rivergate Books, 2005.
Prince, Carl E. Brooklyn's Dodgers: the bums, the borough, and the best of baseball, 1947-1957. Oxford University Press, 1996.
Baseball teams--United States--History; Baseball--United States--History--20th century; Brooklyn Dodgers (Baseball team); Los Angeles Dodgers (Baseball team); National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum; Photographs; Postcards
- Series I: Brooklyn Dodgers
  - Subseries I: Baseballs
    - Baseballs, Autographed, 1941-1944 (Box 1)
    - Baseballs, Autographed, 1945-1948 (Box 2)
    - Baseballs, Autographed, 1949-1952 (Box 3)
    - Baseballs, Autographed, 1953-1957 (Box 4)
    - Baseballs, Autographed, undated (Box 5)
    - Baseballs, Autographed, undated (Box 6)
  - Subseries II: Memorabilia
    - Envelopes, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Patch, Pin and Keychain (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Team Yearbook, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Trading Cards (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Oversize Pennant, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Poster (Folder 1)
  - Subseries III: Ephemera
    - Baseball Magazine, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Game Programs, 1942-1956 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Press, Radio, and TV Guide, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Stamps, Jackie Robinson, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Team Rosters, 1931-1958 (Box 7, Folder 9-11)
    - Tickets, 1942-1955 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Welcome Home Dinner Program, Autographed, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Oversize Spring Training Schedule, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Subseries IV: Clippings
    - Clippings, 1955-1957, 1990-1992 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Subseries V: Correspondence
    - Walter O'Malley to Rud Rennie, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Subseries VI: Prints and Photographs
    - Photographs, Players (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Photographs, Players, Autographed (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Photographs, Team, 1947-1957 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Cartoon, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Postcards, Ebbets Field (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Postcards, Players, Autographed (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Oversize Print, Ebbets Field (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Series II: Non-Brooklyn Baseball Items
  - Subseries I: Memorabilia
    - Baseball Stat Finder, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Baseball Trivia Books, 1975-1994 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
    - Calendars, 1987-1991 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Sticker, New York Giants (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Trading Cards (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Yearbook, Los Angeles Dodgers, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Oversize Paper Dolls Book, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Oversize Ladies Day Sign, Yankees (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II: Ephemera
    - Banquet Program, Autographed, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Brochure, Hotel Homosassa (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Press, Radio, and Television Guides, Los Angeles Dodgers, 1959-1966 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Stamps, 1987-1989 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Tickets, Yankees, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Oversize Placemat, Mets, Autographed (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Subseries III: Clippings
    - Advertisements (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Oversize New York Times Commemorative Edition: The Glory Days of Baseball 1947-1957 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Oversize New York Times, Clippings, 1951-1956 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Subseries IV: Correspondence
      - Box 8
      - Folder 14: Lee Scott to Al, undated
  - Subseries V: Prints and Photographs
    - Postcards, Players and Staff (Box 9)
    - Postcards, Players, Autographed (Box 9)
    - Postcards, Parks and Stadiums (Box 9)
    - Postcards, Book, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, Fans (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Photographs, Players (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, Stadiums (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, Teams, Los Angeles Dodgers and Yankees (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Oversize Prints, Parks and Stadiums (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Subseries VI: The National Baseball Hall of Fame
    - Tickets, 1988-1994 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Program and Newsletters, 1984-1994 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Sticker (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Series III: Non-Baseball Photographs and Prints
  - Postcards, New York City Buildings and Bridges (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Oversize Photograph, Brooklyn Bridge (Box 11, Folder 10)